But if we now come back all the way to
your question in the beginning like what
now determines something as wholesome or
what determines something as unh
wholesome. Well that is that is um fully
up to you discerning whether your mind
is pressing you and that will be an
internal
criteria. And so even if the whole world
says wait what you just did there is
one. If you know that it wasn't coming
out of your mind questioning you, then
from the point of view of Dharma, it
will for you not have been wrong.
Yesterday
um when we were together you
mentioned just briefly about right and
wrong
um about something being right or wrong
as quite black or white.
And um I was just curious about what the
criteria is for something that's right
or wrong
and to kind
of maybe just
clarify. As far as
I see
it, the definition of right is more to
do with it not being wrong.
that most of the
um descriptions in the sutas for example
are more about kind of negative. It's
not this or not that and it kind of
seems that
the rightness is more about what you're
left with once you've
removed these kind of wrong views. So to
to establish the right view, I'm just
curious if
that's seems correct or um if there is
actually something more substantial
there. Yeah. Well, let's find out. Yeah.
So, we were talking about
yesterday about what what makes
something wholesome and what makes
something unh wholesome.
Now perhaps to start there's this famous
oada patimoka vers by the Buddha and
there he starts out by saying refraining
from what is unh wholesome and then it
says doing what is
wholesome and that particular order
there is already significant. So it
starts by seeing and understanding what
is unh
wholesome. Um and by then
gradually understanding that more and
more like recognizing unh wholesome as
unh wholesome which has got various
layers of subtlety to it. Um you will
discern that principle and move towards
an understanding of what is wholesome.
So in your question you you're basically
right you come upon that which is
wholesome by understanding what is unh
wholesome and you can see that in the
gradual training also which begins with
the virtue which is all about starting
out by not doing certain things
um which you might have to take on faith
from the beginning might not be
completely clear what's now wrong with
these things I mean killing and stealing
is right the the the moral precepts are
obviously here but but beyond that what
constitutes something as unh wholesome
that's not the question right so in your
own experience how do you
know whether a certain action by body
speech or mind is wholesome and should
there is unh wholesome and should
therefore be
avoided is the criter
IA are you just going to stick to the
external rules to the formulations that
you have as a monk or if you're a lay
person you're keeping a certain number
of precepts you just keep that
externally you understand what is within
the rule and what is not within the rule
so you just keep the rules and
everything else is automatically fine or
is there a more fundamental criteria
that determines something as unh
wholesome
What would you
say? Well, you would need to start by
holding them externally. Mhm. So that um
because
um like I've heard many times a kind of
definition of what might be unh
wholesome.
But um to think that or you could just
look into the sutras right now and find
a definition of what is unh wholesome,
what is a a more precise
criteria for the answer question. But
that doesn't necessarily mean you can
find that experience or know that in
your experience right from the start.
Yeah. But then what what do the sutas
say isn't awesome? while acting out of
greed, hatred and delusion as a kind of
standard as a as a kind of standard.
Yeah, of course that's a textual answer
which is which is not wrong but in a
sense everybody can say that. So okay.
So then in your experience upholding
those precepts. Yeah. Then it would be
about
discerning
why those things are acting out of
greed, hatred and delusion. Yeah. So
gradually coming closer and closer to
understanding understanding what is yes
understanding what falls within greed
hatred and delusion. Now in your own
experience can you describe what would
make what greed, hatred and let's say
middle-mindedness or delusion what those
three have in common so that you can say
wait that's the wrong direction that is
decline that is deteriorating away from
dharma and so on. What would that be?
What constitutes something as greed, as
hatred, or as middle-mindedness? All the
way from the most
coarse to the most
subtle. There's a bunch of things, but
one of them is like los of of
perspective. like I just get totally
caught in like my thought, the object of
the senses or like whatever is
pressuring me at that moment and there
is like a a pressure to go in that
direction like it feels like I have to
go there because otherwise I feel
like the pressure is felt again if I it
seems like if I don't go there I will I
will I will suffer. It seems like that
seems that if I'm not acting out of like
those things that pressure me, if I
don't go in that direction of where they
pressure me, I'm going to suffer. It
feels like it feels like the natural way
of like going out of that and
those kind of things
um kind
of yeah make me totally lose perspective
and lose the context of my situation
like I lose the sense of what's going on
really.
Yeah. So what is the factor there in all
of this that you just described? What is
the factor based on which you can say
this is unh wholesome because losing
yourself in senses and and and not
having perspective all of that is
already in a sense the result
of of going that in that wrong
direction. So if if you want to um let's
say go upstream so so to speak and and
you want to find out
what which phenomena in your experience
determines
unwome how would you describe
that I guess it's felt as a unpleasant
pressure and that pressure is there
because of you craving It wouldn't
necessarily be that
obvious, but are are you sure this is
it?
Um, craving. Yeah. Mhm. And craving
manifest as pressure.
I'm not saying it's wrong. I'm just
asking.
I wouldn't say I'm not sure if it
manifests as pressure, but but that
pressure is there. Yes. Exactly. Good.
So you find that that pressure is there
if it was yeah if it was that pressure
then I think it would be much easier
to to kind
of well untangle yourself or realize
that you're craving it. Uhhuh. But what
if it is that
pressure?
Um what if acting out of the pressure is
the determining factor for unh
wholesome? Even if the whole world says
it's fine, there's no problem with it.
You can do it. But you clearly see,
wait, my mind is just pushing me now.
The pressure is not
necessarily in your control.
Well, so okay, so we can go into that.
Then I wouldn't be able to free myself.
Wait. Okay, but now that that's a bit of
a
jump. We're just first finding out. So
there's the pressure. Mhm. Yeah. Right.
Now, what if you don't act out of that
pressure? You're aware that your mind is
pushing you in a certain direction,
pressuring you. Yeah. You recognize the
pressure and you make sure that you're
not acting out of it by body speech and
by mind. Mhm. Are you then doing
anything unh wholesome?
No. No. That's right. Even though that
pressure is there. Yeah. Right. So the
unh wholesome action which is always on
you starts when you are acting out of
that
pressure. And it's now important to
realize that in fact your mind cannot
force you to do certain things. You will
always be there giving in and going
along with the pressure. And that is
eventually how you come to recognize the
safety from an allesome because
precisely because it's always up to you.
You can develop yourself so as to not
give into the pressure. So that even in
the face of pressure you will not be
doing anything
unwant. This is why we often talk about
the importance of having that attitude
of
responsibility and fundamentally that is
what the right view then boils down to.
It is seeing beyond doubt what is your
responsibility and what isn't. So acting
out by body speech and mind of that
pressure is what constitutes unh
wholesome action but not the mere
presence of the
pressure. But if you now overshoot it
and say well I don't want to have that
pressure you would just go the other
extreme and you now start basically
attacking your own mind assuming that it
shouldn't be pressure and that you don't
want to be pressured which is ironically
now you acting out of your will towards
your own mind. That is why we often
speak about right endurance that
pressure is there which is in a sense
um well it's not directly of your
making. It's there due to stuff that
you've done in the past, but now you are
stuck with it. So then you just have to
endure it and clearly see that
distinction. Wait, this is mind
pressuring me and now it's up to me
whether I act out of that pressure or
not. And in order to get that
distinction clear, that is precisely the
perspective, the perspective upon your
situation.
And so if there's pressure you cannot
fundamentally not do things. So then the
wisdom is in um learning can I do things
while that pressure is there that are
not um let's say coming out of that
pressure.
Another thing recently I found helpful
was
um not
um when the mind's pressured
and you you know you should really
restrain this tendency to act out. Mhm.
um even if it's not breaking the
precepts or seems
quite remote like kind of what you said
like uh beyond the scope of the precepts
kind of seems like that just
um not seeing any pressure outside the
scope of the precepts in a
sense that makes sense. So that cuz
there's their their thread is the same.
Mhm.
And that if
you
feed if you feed the mind now then and
you keep going in that same direction
then eventually you would break
precepts. Mhm.
Even if it's going for a walk
or muddling with
or getting tangled up with doubt. Um,
still still is it's still the same
trajectory. So, it's a it's a kind
of Yeah, I don't know that. Yeah, I'm
not sure if if I follow, but if by
keeping the pre Look, the whole point of
keeping those precepts is for you to
even begin to recognize what it means to
be pressured by the mind. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Because the starting point is
you'll just be running with it. So you
don't even see it. Then you have various
good reasons for keeping the precepts.
You keep them. And so at some point your
mind wants to push you in that
direction. But now you being committed
to those precepts say, "Wait, I don't
want to go there." So there's going to
be somewhat of an internal quote unquote
conflict between your mind pushing you
in one direction. Then at some point you
went against that fence. Yeah. Which is
those precepts that you're keeping. Now
those precepts, they are in your belfare
if you don't break them. But more
fundamentally their point is that when
you hit in the when you run in the fence
you want to say wait why am I even
running in this direction and so you
turn around and you see a heart was it
basically my my mind pressuring me and
that begins with those eight precepts
and then getting that principle you want
to refine it more and more so so that
you see more clearly your mind
pressuring you that's the whole point of
those precepts and that example that you
mentioned with that monk who is just not
doing anything in wholesome by body
speech and mind yeah If you see to that
degree with such clarity your own mind
and whether it presses you or not then
you don't need any of those rules. You
can just not act then then anything that
comes out of that question will be unh
wholesome and you don't do
it. But then of course you should be
quite clear. Yeah. So when the Buddha
asked that monk, do you see that? Then
basically that monk is declaring himself
to the Buddha to be a noble disciple
because you know Sai Bua when he was
asked in the summer you know how how do
we know what is right? Then the first
thing Suta mentions is well here no
disciple knows the the wholesome and the
root of the wholesome and the unh
wholesome and the root of the unh
wholesome. This is how someone is of
view. So when the Buddha then asks that
particular monk do you see unh wholesome
as unh wholesome and if he then says
fully yes I see all of that to the point
that I can train and not doing anything
unw he was basically already having the
right view so then he was on that middle
way he has understood that principle
okay then just develop
it but we should not be taking any
liberties it's better to uh to be on the
safe side start with those precepts and
then as we discussed now earlier within
that within those boundaries you begin
to refine it. But at the end of the day
it is between you and your mind and when
that relationship is fully clear mind
pressuring you and you can say that
greed hate and illusion or hindus are
just particular manifestations of the
same pressure. That's what they all have
in common.
That relationship you want to fully
clear up and then you do not depend on
anyone in the world, anything external
quote unquote to tell you what's right
and wrong. Because the only criteria for
whether you not do something or not is
whether your own mind is pressuring you
in that direction which is unh
wholesome or whether it's not. And then
there's no issue with it.
And then you and then wherever you are
you keeping an eye on what that own mind
is doing whether it is pressing you or
not you will be able to practice in
every situation regardless. Now it's
still better to be in seclusion because
it will much more easy to recognize
these things. So if you sleep a lot, if
you have a lot of duties, people around,
work to do, talking and so on, you eat
too much, you become uh sleepy, right?
then that will all be an impediment to
keeping an eye on what that cha is up
to. But the whole principle of wholesome
and the root of the wholesome and the
unh wholesome and the root of the unh
wholesome boils down to that. But in
order to even begin to see what is going
on, yeah, you need to start by keeping
those precepts. And then the casual
training also says sense restraint
because to even discern what that mind
is up to, that is in a sense in the
opposite direction of being now lost in
the world of the senses. That mind will
always be peripheral and so you cannot
attend to it directly. Right? This is
all the talks about peripheral
awareness, seeing it indirectly and so
on. But you see directly will always be
object of senses which is why sense
restraint. So
not losing the perspective and just
being lost in objects but bringing it
back sort of here quote unquote will be
necessary because if you're just lost
that way you're not even going to see
what that mind is doing. And of course
it's that same mind pushing you to be
lost there so that it stays out of sight
which is how it has maximum control over
you. So if you want to keep an eye on it
so that you are not the slave of your
own mind, but your mind becomes your
best ally, you have to first pull
yourself out from being lost in the
domain of the senses. Which is why after
the basic virtue which will already save
you out of trouble, sense strains will
be the next thing. and the right
development of yo managara is of course
what's going to be the next step because
acting out of hindrances and attending
from the origin that's mutually
exclusive. So by understanding what the
only money is and developing that you
will be gaining a clearer perspective on
what the innocence are and what is
pressuring you but also right we've
discussed that quite a few times but
just to keep the precepts and not act
out and refine that principle that we
started to talk about in the beginning
is already developing that yo direction
whether you call it that or
not. But if we now come back all the way
to your question in the beginning like
what now determines something as
wholesome or what determines something
as unh wholesome. Well that is that is
um fully up to you discerning whether
your mind is pressing you and that will
be an internal
criteria. And so even if the whole world
says wait what you just did there is
wrong. If you know that it wasn't coming
out of your mind questioning you then
from the point of view of dharma it will
for you not have been wrong.
That's kind of amazing.
Yeah. At the beginning it's threatening
and then it comes
well because true freedom is in the
beginning very threatening
and that sense of independence.
and they go together, right? Freedom,
responsibility, all those things that
they're they're just different facets of
of of the same thing. So to say that you
are fully responsible for everything you
do by body, speech and mind, that
statement has got meaning only. If you
see that in relation to your mind
pressuring you, if you leave that whole
domain out, then you can say, "Yeah, I
take responsibility for what I do." But
that would just be a hollow statement.
If in reality it is your mind pushing
you in this and that direction, then it
doesn't mean anything. Yeah. Because
it's like, oh, I'm responsible, but I
have I don't have the choice but to
react to that pressure. It's like, well,
then you're not responsible at all.
Yeah. So then you can say, I'm I'm
responsible, but but yeah, that just
that's just a joke then. So you you have
to include that and then start training
and taming that mind so that so that
then at some point you will be able to
start telling that mind what to
do. Right? In the beginning it's going
to be a bit of a struggle. You have to
tame and train that mind and it might
not immediately listen. That is why you
need to be patient and so on. But at
some point that mind begins to trust
you. You can see wait mind begins to to
tame that
relationship develops and uh and you
begin to realize that the safety is in
your mind not being able to make you do
things without you giving in. So it is
fully up to you and then you realize
well then the whole training is to train
that mind so that it is no longer
pressuring me in unh wholesome
directions but it will see for itself
that it is much better if it calms down
and then you can just um live happily
together and your mind will be your ally
um rather than something that you need
to keep an eye on because if you don't
you'll end up being in trouble.
Is that freedom from remorse? That kind
of because
it's an aspect of it, not the whole
thing. Yeah. So, so why are you in
remorse about
things? What does the remorse depend
upon?
Well, giving in to the pressure
and then on a later occasion realizing,
wait, that's not right. Yeah. Knowing
it's not right. So, there has to be some
loss of perspective somewhere. Yeah. And
then afterwards you sort of regain it
and you say well that was now no
good. So that is even more reason to
keep an eye on that mind. Sort of what
you what you thought was a form of
safety clearly wasn't a form of safety.
Yeah. So that remorse can then also be a
clear indicator that there's more work
to be done. That is why it is good to
keep questioning. And even in the sutras
for noble disciples that is a recurring
training like uh you know can my
companions find fault with my conduct
and even that is then just in relation
to external things to stuff that other
people can see even that is still a
reflection there then how much more so
you in relation to the to your own
thoughts that you might still be
delighting in and and and welcoming.
That was something I've
uh been interested in because there's a
lot there's actually quite a lot in in
the sutas and definitely a lot in the
vineyard that
um is
clearly aiming at
removing kind of
a kind of social a
remorse a kind of remorse that might
come from quite kind of arbitrary
things.
Um like just about how your ethic or how
a monk should walk. And there's a lot
there's a lot of advice on that which is
doesn't necessarily
um if you just had that you wouldn't
necessarily be pointed in to the right
in the right direction of your
intention. Yeah. So I'm not exactly sure
which ones you are now referring to but
sure. So, so that there is a level of
etiquette and okay then you don't maybe
want to be misrepresenting other monks
with certain behaviors that but you see
then um fundamentally still it seems
like it would still be beneficial
because it wouldn't be there I mean even
if it's
um so you can take that on consider it
um put it into practice but again now
don't just regard that now as external
but you can still try to see like
like could there be something unwant
about those things still like would
there be some restlessness in the mind
or or something else that is not proper
for somebody who is like fully composed
and self-controlled right if you walk
down the street on arms round and you
are and you are just window
shopping right just looking at what's on
sale yeah it's going to be very
difficult if you still have interest in
those things you're sort of missing the
point in terms of your overall
perspective or if you are talking loudly
or you're just laughing and joking. Uh
then then then all of that uh perhaps
not too complicated to to to see that
you know if you want to train yourself
on the level of which thoughts you are
welcoming and not welcoming but then
outwardly you are laughing and and
joking to the point that other people in
the street actually you you you draw
attention from those people. Well, you
cannot be behaving in that way and at
the same time keep an eye on what's
going on mentally.
Um, so that that's the same reason why
seclusion is beneficial. You don't need
to talk to anyone and if you do not need
to talk and break out into speech, it
will be much easier to see your mental
chatter. Not so easy to see your mental
chat when you're talking the whole time.
You you don't see it. uh and in
fact you know whether because just to
break out into speech and say something
can of course also come out of that same
pressure from the mind. So that's the
same training should I now say it or
not. And we did a whole talk on right
speech uh in the past and and it's that
same principle whether something is
wholesome or un wholesome is not
determined by what you say but by the
intention based on which you say it. And
if you feel pressure to say something
then that is what makes it unh wholesome
not the not the words that you are
saying. Even though when the sutra is
there then in the case like okay if it's
if if a piece goes in this direction
will always be wrong just as in the
beginning breaking the precepts well
breaking precepts will always be wrong
you cannot justify breaking those
precepts and then say yeah well that was
any pressure that's impossible so those
outer boundaries are there just to show
you the main principle and then it's up
to you like okay now develop that same
principle that's now coming into sight
on account of you being committed to
those precepts
speeds and then you just fully apply it
to the mental level as
well and that's just takes that that is
training and that takes also reviewing
and it's good to just make time for that
at the end of the day and consider which
conversation did I have what did I talk
about did I right do I still recollect
acting out of pressure uh and to just
get in the habit of reflecting in that
way and then it will be over time it
will become easier to catch yourself
while you are in that situation because
that is fundamentally where the
restraint that needs to happen.
Yeah. I think like just yeah to go back
to the the remorse and what you say now
is that
um well like this practice of like what
just you just just mentioned like kind
of recollecting what kind of action what
kind of speech and eventually what kind
of s kind of was cultivating during the
day is like basically to kind of
cultivate a sense of shame like
cultivate the right sense of shame and
remorse doesn't happen automatically
it's just kind of like forgetting
literally this very sense of shame
because like if I was shameful enough
this action I would have actually
avoided and basically like now I'm
ashamed of having lacking my sh enough
shame so I I just act out of like
shamelessness really and I just act out
on those ways and that's why it feels
like difficult because now I have to
kind of recollect and feel that shame it
has to be felt like and that's painful
and it have to be felt like without
trying to get rid of it or and certainly
not justifying it just like kind of
feeling it and and take the
determination say okay next time I won't
do it but now I did so I have to enjoy
the things and I think that's why it's
very like those practice are so
beneficial but at the same time yeah
kind of hard like because you have to
kind of enjoy the things over and over
again and
yeah like this attitude of like
justifying the mind like the mind trying
to find justification and things like
that it seems much more easy but that's
the very reason why because I was
justifying myself that's the very reason
why I give to those actions that now I
feel shameful of so like I think it kind
of also follow like what you were saying
before I can it's black and white you
cannot do both at the same time whether
I kind of cultivate the sense of of
shame or I just that's okay that's all
right you either cover it you're either
recovering it or you are learning to see
and that is also writes right for a
noble disciple that's one of the first
faculties that the Buddha often talks
about shame and the right so the right
shame based on the correct understanding
and now the fear of wrongdoing right
fear of wrongdoing like not wanting to
now start agitating that mind that you
basically were taming
um so yeah that's good and and it even
says in the context of monks and their
precepts like even if you uh you know
break those precepts. Um uh I mean it's
better to not do do that but uh but but
if you uh uh let's say break one of
those precepts Yeah. than to uh to
correct them well to realize that you
made a mistake, confess it, correct it
and then determine to not do it again.
And then the Buddha says, "Yeah, this is
how there's progress in Dharma."
Basically, just what you described. Now
that whole same principle applies even
if you do not break any of the precepts
that have been formulated. But as we
said at some point you want to keep that
same attitude until even on the level of
the thoughts that you welcome and
delight in or the things that you
anticipate at some point it will come to
that and and then you say wait I don't
want to delight in it I don't want to
welcome it and yeah then there are
certain discourses that deal with um how
to remove obstructing thoughts and
that's going to be a whole separate
discussion like because thoughts can
arise on their own. So you have to
endure but at some point you will also
recognize wait I'm actually now feeding
those thoughts and that you should
stop and we can call it thought but
there's a bit of a there's further
development there but we can discuss
that perhaps on another occasion. Yeah,
but all of that will depend on um
understanding what we're saying now
because it's essential for the mind, not
different than when you started with the
precepts for the body and speech, which
is why it's a gradual training.